<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proposal for maintaining and repairing the high ways by E. Littleton.</title>
            <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12618636</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12618636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 964:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proposal for maintaining and repairing the high ways by E. Littleton.</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Roads --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roads --  Great Britain --  Finance.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64448:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64448:1"/>
            <p>A PROPOSAL FOR Maintaining and Repairing THE HIGH WAYS.</p>
            <p>By E. LITTLETON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposal">
            <pb facs="tcp:64448:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64448:2"/>
            <head>A PROPOSAL FOR THE HIGH WAYES.</head>
            <p>IT is moſt certain, that the High Wayes of <hi>England</hi> are extremely bad at preſent. And it is as certain, that this badneſs of the High Wayes is a great and publick Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience; ſo that it much concernes us to have them mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But this cannot be done without Charge. For the Wayes muſt ſtill ly in the ill condition they are in, if we will not be at the Charge to repair them. The way to have the Work well done, is by raiſing Money for that purpoſe, and laying it out in due Method. For the ſcambling way of ſending in Carts and Labourers will never do it. Nor will it ever be done by ſingle Pariſhes: tho you fine them over and over, for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then they are able. And ſurely it ſeemes a hard caſe, that when a great and foule Road paſſeth through a Corner of a poor Pariſh; thoſe people muſt maintain it whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can or no, when perhaps themſelves have the leaſt Uſe of it. But a Hundred can do thoſe things, which a Pariſh cannot do: and what the Hundred cannot, the County can. Tho ſome things there are, that to be done as they ſhould, would be too great a burthen to a County: and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Aſſiſtance of the whole Kingdom. Which, tho given in a very ſmall and eaſy proportion, would perform great matters.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64448:3"/>
            <p>It is therefore humbly propoſed;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a conſtant yearly Tax be laid upon Land of four pence in the pound.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Collectors of it in each Pariſh pay the one moie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Pariſh Surveyor, and the other moiety to the Surveyor of the Hundred.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Surveyor of the Hundred employ the one half of his moiety upon the Wayes within his Limits, and pay over the other half to the Surveyor of the County.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the County Surveyor remit one quarter part of his Money to the Surveyor General of <hi>England;</hi> employing the reſidue upon the Bridges and great Roads of the County.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the Surveyor General employ his whole Money in the <hi>London</hi> Roads, the whole Kingdom being concern'd in them.</p>
            <p>There is great reaſon to hope and believe, that ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Tax, diſpoſed of in this manner, would make wondrous Alterations for the better in a few years. It would make the Wayes of <hi>England</hi> another thing from what they are now.</p>
            <p>The Pariſhes will have two pence in the pound, to lay out upon thoſe Wayes that are particularly moſt uſeful to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And when they have done this, they have done their whole Duty: nor are they to be now puniſh'd or moleſted upon the account of High Wayes. As for ſuch of their Wayes as are uſeful to others alſo, they will be maintain'd (or help'd to be maintain'd) by thoſe others: that is, by the Hundred or the County. Moreover every Pariſhioner will have benefit, by what is done by and in the Pariſh.</p>
            <p>The Surveyor of the Hundred will have a penny a pound from the whole Hundred: To be laid out in thoſe Wayes that are moſt uſeful to the Hundred. Of which the particular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and every particular Man, will have the benefit.</p>
            <p>The County Surveyor will have three farthings a pound from the whole County. Which will alſo redound to the benefit of the particular Hundreds and Pariſhes, and of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Man.</p>
            <p>The Surveyor General will have a farthing in the pound
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64448:3"/>from the whole Kingdom: to make good the Roads (where it is needful) from all parts to <hi>London.</hi> which will be a great benefit and advantage, both to the Counties, and to the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and Pariſhes. to all Men in general, and to every Man in particular.</p>
            <p>The Pariſhes therefore need not grudge, that the half of their Tax is carried from them; ſince the whole is employed for their Good.</p>
            <p>The Summe to be laid out by the Surveyor of an ordinary Pariſh will be under ten pound. For the yearly value of all <hi>England</hi> is about ten Millions, (tho ſome think it twelve Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions or more:) and the Pariſhes we know are neere ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. Which gives a thouſand pound a Yeare to each Pariſh, taking one with another. And a thouſand two pences make eight pound and a Noble.</p>
            <p>The Summe to be laid out by the Surveyor of an ordinary Hundred may be threeſcore or fourſcore pound. And the Surveyor of an ordinary midling County may have about ſix Hundred pound. But the Surveyor General will have at leaſt ten thouſand pound yearly. For ten Millions of Farthings make ſomething above that Summe.</p>
            <p>In a great Pariſh there may be two or more Surveyors; and ſo in a great Hundred, and in a great County.</p>
            <p>The Pariſh Surveyors may be choſen by the Pariſhes, as now they are: and they may have liberty to lay out their Money (as far as it will go) in what part they pleaſe. But the Survey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors of the Hundreds and Counties, may be by the Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and under the Direcetion, of the Juſtices. And the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor general may be under the Governance, and by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, of ſuch Perſons as the Parliament ſhall pleaſe to appoint; or may even deſerve the Care of his Majeſty and Councel.</p>
            <p>Let me adviſe both the greater and leſſer Surveyors, to do their work ſubſtantially as far as they go. And what is now left undone, may be done another time. But a thing done ſlightly is good for nothing. A due thickneſs of Stones and Gravel, may (with a little reparation) laſt for ever: whereas too ſmall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64448:4"/>a Quantity will ſoon be ſwallowed up in the Dirt, and no ſigne left of it. Moreover where the Ground is falſe, and rotten, and of the nature of a Quagmire; all the coſt and labour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon it is meerly loſt, unleſs you lay faggots or bavins of Bruſh wood, acroſſe and under the made Way. And in this and all other ſorts of ground, it muſt be a principall care to lay the Wayes dry: ſo that no water may run along them or over them, or ly upon them.</p>
            <p>Beſide the ordinary Work which is done to the High Wayes, there are three things that will greatly conduce to their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment: That is to ſay, Turning, Opening, and Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>The Turning of a Way in ſome places will make it much better, and in ſome places will make it alſo much ſhorter. A Surveyor therefore, with the approbation and conſent of two or three of the next Juſtices, ſhould have power to do it: he making Satisfaction to the Land-Owners, out of the Tax-Money he hath to lay out. And if he and the Owners cannot agree it, then a Jury to be empannell'd (by the Surveyor or the next Juſtice) to determine the matter. But 'tis likely a good part of this Satisfaction muſt be allowed by thoſe, through whoſe Lands the old way did go, and who now are eas'd of it.</p>
            <p>The Opening and Widening of the Wayes is highly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in the Incloſed Countries: where the Roads generally are too narrow, and in many places ſhaded with Trees. Which things as they have extremely ſpoyl'd the Roads hitherto, ſo the removing of theſe things would go a great way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Cure. I confeſs, in ſtrictneſs, they that have thus ſtreighten'd the Wayes (that is the Owners of the Lands adjoyning) might be compell'd to open them. But it may ſeeme too hard: whereas no hardſhips are here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. And the making new Fences would be more grievous to them, then their loſs of Land. It ſeems there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt equall that this Charge be divided. Let the Owners allow more Land, and the Surveyor make the Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Or if the Owners will do this themſelves, the Surveyor to give them a juſt Conſideration for it. The Land, I ſaid,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64448:4"/>muſt be allowed by the Owners: that is, ſo much as will give the Wayes a reaſonable breadth. But if the breadth be extraordinary, the Surveyor to pay for the extraordinary Land that makes it. You will ſay, If the Roads be widen'd in this manner, many a fine Row of Trees muſt go to wrack. To which I anſwer; that it is very good Husbandry, to cut down Trees full grown, and plant young ones in their ſtead. But it ſeems a little unfortunate, that ſuch care hath been taken to plant Trees, where they may do moſt Miſchief. The planting of Trees upon High Wayes is the ſame ſort of Wit, as the building of Houſes upon Bridges. for both of them deſtroy the End for which High Wayes and Bridges are ordain'd, that is, convenience of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. Yet I confeſs that Trees on the North ſide a Way do little harme. in regard they only keep off the Sun for part of the day in the height of Summer, when the Wayes can beſt ſpare it.</p>
            <p>When I ſpeak of Levelling the High Wayes, my meaning is, That by abating the Hills and raiſing the Hollowes and Vallies, the Wayes may be brought neerer to a Levell then now they are: and that ſo the Aſcents and Deſcents may be made more eaſie. And here (which is a great advantage) two things will be done at once. For the ſame Earth that is taken from the Hills, will be carried down to the Hollowes. And by this meanes, if the Hill be cut downe ſix foot, and the Hollow raiſed as much; the Aſcent will be made eaſier by twelve foot.</p>
            <p>A few Carts will carry abundance of Earth in a ſhort time, going not far and down the Hill. If it ſhould be half a mile, (and it will ſeldome be ſo much); each Cart may eaſily carry ten load a day, provided it be fill'd quick. Which that it may be, we ſhould uſe the way of <hi>Barbados:</hi> where Induſtry is at the heighth, and where they ſtudy to carry on great Works to moſt advantage.</p>
            <p>They do there make great Walls or Weares, in the low places where there comes a good ſtream of Floud-Water; thereby to ſtop the running Mould that is waſht from their Land. And without theſe Walls, there is in many of thoſe low places a mighty depth of rich Mould. This Mould (however it come to be there) they carry out to their Grounds neer adjacent. to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64448:5"/>manure them for planting. And when they go about it, they do not (as we do in <hi>England</hi>) ſet two or three Fellowes to throw up the Earth into a Cart with Spades, ſo that one Cart would be an houre in loading; but their way is this. Foure or five good How-men a breaſt lead the way, and fall upon this Earth with their Howes: cutting it down (after they are a little enter'd into it) half a yard deep or more; and each Man taking about a yard in breadth. And ſo they paſs on, leaving behind them the looſe Mould they have digg'd. After theſe How-men come nine or ten Fillers (part Men, part Women) with every one a Box. which is nothing elſe but a broad board at the bottome, with narrower boards at the ſides and one end, the other end and the top being left open. Into theſe Boxes, at the open end, they pull the looſe Mould with broad Howes. and (with the help of one another) getting it up upon their heads, away they go with it to the Cart; which ſtands cloſe by, with the Carter up in the taile of it. Who ſwiftly takes the Mould from off their heads, throwes it into the Cart, and gives back the empty Boxes. Thus the work goes on merrily: And by that time each Filler hath brought foure Boxes, the Cart is loaded: and preſently drives away, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cart being ready. which they quickly ſerve in the ſame manner. And three or foure Carts, plied in this manner, will carry out in few dayes a mighty quantity of Earth. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over when the How-men have gone as far as is convenient, they then come back: and either begin a new breadth, or go over the firſt breadth againe.</p>
            <p>In the work here deſcribed, the How-men are but foure or five, when the Fillers are nine or ten: becauſe of the ſoftneſs and eaſineſs of the ground. But in the Roads of <hi>England,</hi> where the ground is harder, there muſt be as many How-men as Fillers: or rather more. And eight or nine Inches may be found a ſufficient depth, to go on with at one time. Alſo whereas in the <hi>Barbadian</hi> Affaire there is mention made of Howes, that ſort of Tooles is little uſed in <hi>England.</hi> But in ſuch work as pulling down Hills, and cutting through Hills, I account it much better than the Spade. The rather, becauſe theſe Works muſt be carried on in Summer; when generally all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64448:5"/>ground is hard, ſo that a Spade can hardly touch it. And withall it will looke moſt proper and natural, when the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men go on forward up the Hill, the Earth they have digged being ſtill carryed away from behind them.</p>
            <p>In the great Roads, the breadth of theſe cut Wayes ſhould be about twenty yards. which will take up twenty How-men abreaſt at once, or ten at twice. This (I think) ſhould be the breadth; beſide the Splay, which may be made laſt. And the rais'd ground below may have the like breadth, beſide the Slope. But where the heighth of the rais'd ground is more then ordinary, there ſhould be no Slope, but a Wall on each ſide.</p>
            <p>In this kind of Worke, a Man of Skill will know before hand, how many load of Earth the low ground will require, to be raiſed to ſuch a heighth; and how many load the high ground, cut down to ſuch a depth, will yield. And he will ſo order it, that when the Work is brought to the Line pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, there ſhall not a Spade-full of Earth be either to ſpare or wanting.</p>
            <p>If neer to a Hill there be a Hollow, that is, ſuch a low ground as riſes preſently on the other ſide, and a Way goes throu the Hollow over the Hill; that Hollow will eaſily be raiſed. And if from the brow of the Hill the ground ſoon falls as you go further on, that Hill may be eaſily cut throu and abated. And by both or either of theſe things the Aſcent is made leſs. But if both the high ground and the low ground be a great continued Plain; in this caſe the Aſcent cannot be made leſs, but yet it may be made more eaſy. For Example: There is a Hill twenty yards high: and as the Slope is now, you go a hundred yards to mount it. So that you riſe one yard in five. But if the brow of the Hill be cut throu, and the Aſcent be carried (by an eaſier Slope) fifty yards farther on; if alſo, by laying this Earth at the bottome, the Aſcent is made begin fifty yards farther back; you muſt now go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward two hundred yards to get up the twenty yards in heighth, and you will riſe now but one yard in ten.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64448:6"/>
            <p>This kind of Work belongs only to the greater Surveyors, and chiefly to the Surveyor General. who with his ten thouſand pound a year will do wonders. He will do ſuch things as our Forefathers never dream'd of.</p>
            <p>Let us now conſider the Coſt and Charge of theſe Workes. In a great piece of Work, or a Jobb of the firſt magnitude, there may be ten Carts, twenty Howers or Diggers, and as many Fillers. The Carts will need but three Horſes a piece, in regard they go down the Hill when they are loaden, and and come up empty. However, to reckon largely, we may allow ten Shillings a day for each Cart: which for the ten Carts is five pound a day. And the Wages of the Diggers and Fillers, with the Salaries of thoſe that Over-ſee the Worke, and other Incidents, may come to another five pound. which makes ten pound in the whole. Ten pound a day is ſixty pound a Week, ſix hundred pound in ten weekes, twelve hundred pound in twenty, and eighteen hundred in thirty. which I think are as many weekes as are proper for ſuch work in one yeare. The firſt ten weekes will make a great Notch in the top of a Hill, and lay a great Heap at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. enough to cure any ordinary Steep. But if ten weekes will not perfect the buſineſs, perhaps twenty will: and that which cannot be done in twenty weekes, may be done in thirty. And ſurely there are few places, that will not by the Labour of thirty weekes receive a very great amendment. <hi>Labor omnia vincit Improbus.</hi> this <hi>Improbus labor</hi> will do ſtrange things.</p>
            <p>We ſee an Example of raiſing a Hollow, at <hi>Fleet</hi> Bridge. From whence, in former times, it was a hard Steep up <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> Hill, and not much better up <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> But by making the Bridge higher, and filling up the ground at each end, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is now made eaſie both wayes.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew what Money can do in theſe Matters, I ſhall give two Inſtances. The one is, That during the times of the Uſurpation, they in ſome places tax'd the Pariſhes by a pound rate, for repairing the High Wayes. Particularly it was done
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64448:6"/>in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> about <hi>Lemſter:</hi> where the Tax was no leſs then ſix pence a pound. This way did not laſt long. but it did ſo effectually do the buſineſs, and it wrought ſuch a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the like was never there ſeen before or ſince. The other Inſtance is, in what hath lately been done in <hi>Kent,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Canteerbury</hi> Road. which they have made very ſubſtantially good, where it was extremely bad before, by a ſmall Tax of about a half-penny in the pound laid upon the County.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the ſum here propoſed to be conſtantly payd, that is a groat in the pound, may ſeem at firſt hearing too great a burden. But either I am exceedingly miſtaken, or it will be found and deem'd (upon tryall) the beſt money that ever was beſtowed. ſo ſudden, ſo great, ſo generall, will the benefit be. However if it be thought too much, let it be the half, or even leſs then half. but then the work will not be half ſo well done.</p>
            <p>It would be a great help toward the charge of the High Wayes, if there were Tolls erected, in fit places, and where they are needfull. And ſurely it ſeemes juſt and equall, that thoſe ſhould give ſomething toward ſuch work, who have a preſent benefit by it. A Toll therefore is not to be payd to make the way good hereafter, (for many that go there now, will perhaps never come that way again, and ſo would have nothing for their Money); but the Way muſt be firſt made good, and then the Toll payd. Which thing may be eaſily ſo order'd. For there will be People, we need not doubt, that will advance Money for ſuch Works, to be reimburs'd with Intereſt out of the Toll: and then the Toll to continue no longer. Alſo a Toll for High Wayes mended, ſhould be payd only in thoſe Months, in which the Wayes would otherwiſe be bad. For the Traveller hath then a preſent benefit. But 'tis hard to pay Toll in Summer, for a Way that was foule only in Winter. A Toll is moſt proper, when a Bridge is made, where there was only a Ferry before. And people in that caſe may well afford to pay a Toll; if it be ſomething leſs, then what they muſt otherwiſe have payd for Ferrying.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64448:7"/>
            <p>I have ſaid already, and ſay again now, that the Surveyor General, with his ten thouſand pound a yeare, will do great matters. I ſuppoſe the firſt thing he will do, will be the Paving or Pitching the Towns Ends here about <hi>London:</hi> which now ly in ſuch a beaſtly pickle. to the annoyance of the people of the whole Kingdome, who are perpetually coming in hither and going out hence, on all ſides. The reparation of theſe Pavings may be put upon thoſe who are to maintain the Wayes. And ſurely the Charge of the Gravell that is carried yearly to theſe Wayes, to little purpoſe, will eaſily repaire the Pavings.</p>
            <p>In the next place, this Surveyor ('tis like) will fall upon <hi>Shooters</hi> Hill. The Steep, which is the thing to be remedied, is on the farther ſide: and at the bottome of it there is a ſmall Hollow. If this Hollow were filled up, ſo as to begin the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent at the further Edge, it would be a great advantage. But we muſt not run up to the Beacon, as now we do, where the Hill is higheſt; for an eaſy compaſs to the right hand, (throu the Wood), will bring us to the top of the Hill, where it is much lower then where the Way goes now. Alſo this Hill may be cut quite throu: it preſently falling on the other ſide, that is, on the ſide next <hi>London.</hi> and the Earth will fill the Hollow before ſpoken of. I ſuppoſe one ten weeks Labour, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the rate above deſcribed, will abundantly do this whole Buſineſs. But this new Way muſt go upon new Ground, which muſt be payd for. I anſwer, that the Coſt will not be great. Every Acre will come to ten pound: reckoning it at ten ſhillings an Acre, and at twenty yeares purchaſe. and the new Way cannot take up three Acres. Alſo this new Way will not be far about: and neer as much will be ſaved in the up hill and down hill, as will be loſt in the compaſs.</p>
            <p>The going up to <hi>Black Heath</hi> is not ſo bad a place as <hi>Shooters</hi> Hill, but yet is more difficult to cure. However it may be helped very much; By widening the paſſage that is there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: By cutting throu the Brow of the Hill, and carrying the Aſcent on further; And by employing all this Earth, to raiſe the Way below quite to <hi>Deptford</hi> Bridge. from whence the Aſcent ſhould begin, and be gently carried on. Alſo this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64448:7"/>Bridge ſhould be made a little higher: and likewiſe broader, and every way better. For it is a ſhame to ſee ſuch a pitifull pimping Bridge, upon a great Road, ſo neere our Capital City. The Surveyor may beſtow upon this piece of Work, full ten Weeks Labour, or more if he pleaſe. And he will alſo be out Money, beſide the Coſt at the Bridge, for removing ſome Houſes upon the Road below; which ſtreighten the Road, and will hinder its convenient raiſing.</p>
            <p>About a Mile ſhort of <hi>Deptford,</hi> as you go from <hi>London</hi> thither, the Road to <hi>Tunbridge</hi> turns off upon the right hand. where you preſently climbe a ſteep Hill; and afterwards you go down another Steep, upon <hi>Leuſham Bridge.</hi> But if you went further on in <hi>Deptford</hi> Way, and then turn'd to the right hand; the Hill would be avoided, and the way would go to that <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham Bridge,</hi> almoſt upon plain ground. Our Surveyor therefore will probably take care of this matter, among the firſt. The Land that this new Way will go upon, may be eight or ten Acres: which will coſt twenty or thirty pound an Acre; in all, two or three hundred pound. And this is no ſuch frightful Summe to a Surveyor General. Moreover the Surveyor muſt pay for making the Fences on both ſides the new Way. And he ſhould make a better Bridge at <hi>Leuſham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particular Works already mention'd, will be for the ſervice and benefit of the Men of <hi>Kent.</hi> So likewiſe it will be a ſervice to the <hi>Eſſexians</hi> and <hi>Eaſt Angles,</hi> to have <hi>Bow Bridge</hi> made better. And ſurely a handſome and noble paſſage in this place, would alſo be an Ornament to the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> and to the whole Kingdome likewiſe. For ſuch Publick Workes are Markes of a Peoples Wealth and Greatneſs: giving alſo a Taſt of their Spirit and Genius. But to return to our buſineſs; the Main Bridge at <hi>Bow</hi> is very firm and ſtrong, and of a good heighth. But the made way beyond it over the Low Grounds, with the Bridges upon the leſſer Channels of the River, are but juſt enough to make the Way paſſable. Which therefore looks like a Way leading to a Mill, or at moſt to ſome little Market Town; and not like a great Road, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly (and at a very cloſe diſtance) to the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64448:8"/>our Nation. The thing that is here to be done, is to make this Way ſomething higher and broader, with a handſome Wall on each ſide, and handſome Bridges over the leſſer Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells. Alſo the Hollow on this ſide the main Bridge ſhould be fill'd up: which would make the Aſcent more eaſy and leſs dirty. And Earth may be had (for this and all the reſt) out of the next Fields toward <hi>London,</hi> where they now digg Gravell. I doubt this Work, to be well done, will coſt three or foure thouſand pound.</p>
            <p>The Northern Men muſt be ſerved next: and there is a tough Jobb to be done for them, which is, the curing of <hi>Highgate Hill.</hi> There are two Wayes from <hi>London</hi> to go up this Hill; the one by <hi>Iſlington,</hi> the other by <hi>Pancras.</hi> From <hi>Iſlington</hi> you go along a deep rotten bottome, and then come to a terrible hard and long Steep: at which many a poor Horſe hath had his Heart broken. Upon the whole matter, we muſt allow it to be a very bad place. And what remedy is there for it? Truly if we keep the old way, we may lay out a great deale of Money to little pupoſe. But a Ridge of high ground (the ſame that faces <hi>London</hi>) goes declining from <hi>Highgate</hi> towards <hi>Hornſey.</hi> And if a new Way were carried on (between the preſent way to <hi>Highgate</hi> and the way to <hi>Hornſey,</hi> but neerer to <hi>Hornſey</hi> Way) to the ſaid Ridge, where it is many Yards lower then the top of <hi>Highgate</hi> over which the great Road goes now; and likewiſe if this Ridge were cut throu, and the Earth carried down to raiſe the Way below; the Aſcent would then be eaſy ſo farr. But ſtill there remain ſeveral other Ridges, and ſeveral Hollowes: which muſt be all made level, or brought neer the Levell, by cutting throu the Ridges and filling the Hollowes; till we come into <hi>Barnet</hi> Road, half a Mile or more beyond and below <hi>Highgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Way by <hi>Pancras,</hi> it is a vile Way, and no way becoming the Metropolis of a great Kingdome. We muſt therefore endeavour to make it better. In the firſt place, when we come to a Watercourſe about half a Mile out of Town, we muſt not go creeping along this Watercourſe, as we do now; but we muſt lay a good Bridge over it, and keep
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64448:8"/>upon the higher ground on the right hand. In the next place, whereas there is a great Hollow juſt beyond <hi>Kentiſh Towne,</hi> that Hollow muſt be filled up: as likewiſe a leſſer Hollow a little further on. For otherwiſe we muſt go down into them. And to go down hill when we ſhould be going up hill, is dead loſs. Thirdly, when we are paſt theſe Hollowes, we muſt not go up the ſteep Hill to <hi>Highgate,</hi> but keep to the left hand, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the lower ground, till we come to the Way that croſſes from <hi>Highgate</hi> to <hi>Hampſted.</hi> Fourthly, beyond this Way is a high and narrow Ridge of ground: and this Ridge muſt be cut thorow. Which Earth will fill up in a great meaſure the Hollowes below. and what is wanting may be otherwiſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. Fifthly, from the Notch here made, the Way will go upon pretty even ground, bowing a little to the Right; till it come in to <hi>Barnet</hi> Road, about the place where <hi>Iſlington</hi> Way comes in. And this is the place where the Innes will be. And whereas formerly <hi>Iſlington</hi> Way and <hi>Pancras</hi> Way did part on the top of <hi>Highgate,</hi> they will now part here; the one going on one ſide of <hi>Highgate,</hi> and the other going on the other ſide. And both <hi>Highgate</hi> and its Hill will be wholly avoided. For you muſt take notice, That we are not now making Ways to <hi>Highgate;</hi> but to <hi>Barnet,</hi> and ſo to S. <hi>Albans,</hi> and all the North-Weſt of <hi>England.</hi> The making theſe two Wayes may coſt ten thouſand pound: but the Money were well beſtowed, if they ſhould coſt ten thouſand pound each.</p>
            <p>The South-Country Men are concern'd in <hi>Portſmouth</hi> Road: which truly is a very bad one. But two places eſpecially will cry out to our Surveyor for ſpeedy help. One of theſe places is a few Miles beyond <hi>Godalming.</hi> When you have gone a while upon the higher and open ground, you paſs over a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond Damme: and I think there is a Way likewiſe above the Pond. But when you have paſt this Water, inſtead of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on to the South, which is the direct courſe, you turn ſhort to the left hand Eaſterly, and climbe a Sandy Hill for almoſt a Mile. And then you turn about to the right hand Weſterly; down a Hill likewiſe, but with an eaſier Slope. All which is done, to avoid (and get to the head of) a deep narrow Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64448:9"/>which lies juſt acroſſe the direct way or courſe. And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, the ſides of this Valley are ſo ſteep, that (as things ſtand now) there is no going that way. But if the Surveyor Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall take this place to taske, with his whole ſtrength before deſcribed, he will perfect the Cure in one Summer. ſo that the Road may croſs this Valley, without much up hill or down-hill, and in a Line not much bending. But the way and manner of doing the thing, is too long to be here ſet downe.</p>
            <p>The other bad place upon this Road is further on towards <hi>Portſmouth:</hi> how much further I do not remember. but the manner of it is this. As you go on from <hi>London,</hi> you ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you a high ſteep Hill. and coming neerer, you find inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a narrow Ridge of ground, twenty or thirty foot high: between which and the Hill there is a Hollow or ſmall Valley. You do not croſs over this Ridge: but keepe under it to the right hand, till you come to the End of it. and then you turn to the Left, and come to the foot of the Main Hill. Where you find ſuch a deſperate Steep, being a very long one withall, and the Way alſo being hollow and narrow; that the like is hardly to be ſeen upon any Road. So that in ſhort the place is next Neighbour to impaſſable. But if you were got to the top of the Ridge before mentioned, which I ſaid is twenty or thirty foot high, and to which a Way is ſoon made; if alſo you were got up as many foot more, in croſſing the ſaid Valley to the main Hill, the way ſtill riſing from the top of the Ridge; and if the top of the main Hill were cut throu, and the Earth or Chalk (for it is a Chalky hill) were carried downe into the Valley, and there laid with a Wall on each ſide; by theſe things the Hill would be wonderfully tamed, and the Aſcent made gentle and eaſy. Here let me adde; that the Brow of this Hill may be cut throu to better advantage, and the Notch made deeper, in regard the ground falls preſently (tho gently) on the other ſide. And I conceive this piece of Work may be done in leſs then a Summer</p>
            <p>But there are places neerer <hi>London</hi> upon this <hi>Portſmouth</hi> Road (where it is alſo the Road to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi>) that deſerve our Surveyors care. in particular the Way to <hi>Kingſton:</hi> which is very uneven. But the Survey or General would ſoon change
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64448:9"/>the face of things. There is a deep bottome at <hi>Richmond</hi> Park Wall: which by reaſon of its broadneſs ſeemes hard to cure. However a full ſtrength of twenty Howmen with the appurtenances, by abating the Hills on each ſide and a little raiſing this Bottome, would make a great alteration for the better in one Summer. And the Aſcent from this Bottome to <hi>Putney</hi> Heath would be made equal and eaſy, which is now very hard at the upper end.</p>
            <p>A Bridge at <hi>Putney</hi> will build it ſelf, without the help of Projectors, if our Surveyor General lay out the Money, to be reimburſed by a Toll. which will do it in a few yeares. And the Toll may be renewed for a time neceſſary, when the Bridge wants repairing. Moreover the making this Bridge at <hi>Putney</hi> will give a ſenſible Advance, to the Lands and Houſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts beyond the Water. and therefore the Owners ought to contribute. For it ſeemes unreaſonable, that particular perſons ſhould receive great Advantage by a Publick Work, and pay nothing towards it. This Advance will be known ſoon after the Bridge is finiſh'd: for it will be notorious. And it may be found by an Inquiſition duely made. I think the Owners may afford to give the one half, of what their Eſtates are clearly and evidently made better: keeping the other half to themſelves, as cleer Gaines. If Land be worth more by three ſhillings an Acre, let it pay eighteen pence: and if a Houſe be worth more by forty ſhillings a yeare, let it pay twenty. to be ſettled upon it as a Rent; but the Rent to be bought off, when the Party pleaſes, at fifteen or ſixteen years purchaſe. If the one half be thought too much, let it be leſs: but they ſhould pay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if the Advance be conſiderable. Otherwiſe it is not worth the looking after.</p>
            <p>Let us now looke upon <hi>Worceſter</hi> Road: where alſo there is Work for the Surveyor Generall. I mean ſuch things as cannot be done by the other Surveyors. This Road, as far as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> is pretty good: only there are three Hollowes or nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Vallies which it croſſes, which may be cured after the manner of <hi>Fleet-Bridge.</hi> That is, the Bridges may be made ſomething higher, and the ground raiſed at each end; ſo as to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64448:10"/>have the Aſcents both wayes, to begin immediately at and from the Bridges. The firſt of theſe Hollowes is a little beyond <hi>Tyburn,</hi> where a ſmall River falls into <hi>Hide-Park:</hi> the ſecond is at <hi>Acton,</hi> and the third at <hi>Brent-Bridge</hi> three miles beyond. But the Road from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> to <hi>Wickham</hi> (for I will now look no farther) is very untoward: going over high and rugged ground. and there is no good way to cure it, but by turning it. If you ask where and how this turning muſt be, I'le tell you. As we come from <hi>Wickham</hi> toward <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> we keep along the Vallie for two Miles and more, and then we mount to the higher ground: where we quickly meet with a deep Hollow. From the bottome whereof we turn to the Left hand towards <hi>Beaconsfield,</hi> up a hard and a long Hill, which brings us into a Common. But if this Hollow were quite fill'd up, (as it might) and the brow of the oppoſite Hill cut throu; we might go ſtraight forward, by a ſhort and eaſy Aſcent, to another part of the ſame Common. And then, inſtead of turning to the Left Hand to <hi>Beconsfield,</hi> we might keep to the Right Hand, and fall into the Road that goes between <hi>Wickham</hi> and <hi>Windſor.</hi> Which will quickly bring us to a Range of plain dry Commons, all of the ſame Levell. along which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons there lies a direct way to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge:</hi> about half a Mile ſhort of it, coming in to <hi>Beconsfield</hi> Road. I grant that here alſo are ſome Hollowes: but they may be eaſily cured. So that upon the whole matter, it will be one of the pleaſanteſt Roads within forty Miles of <hi>London.</hi> And whereas it may be thought a great way about, it will be found very little. For the ſtraight Line to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> from the deep Hollow before mention'd, goes between <hi>Beconsfield</hi> Road and the new Road here intended. And <hi>Beconsfield</hi> Road bowes neer as much to the Left, as the other does to the right.</p>
            <p>I come now to <hi>Hampſted</hi> Road; which I confeſs is but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate one, in compariſon of thoſe others before named. But it will be for the Glory of our <hi>Metropolis,</hi> and of great Uſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all (for abundance of Horſes, Carts, and Coaches, are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually paſſing that Way;) to have it made eaſy, and handſome, and noble. Which (I acknowledge) is a very difficult piece of Worke. The beſt way to do it, in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64448:10"/>henſion, is this. When we are come from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Totten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Court,</hi> we muſt not ſink on the right hand down into the Bottom, as we do now, which makes the Aſcent afterward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely hard; but we muſt go ſtraight on upon the Wind Mill, keeping ſtill (by this meanes) on the higher ground. I confeſs the ground here is very uneven: which I ſuppoſe is the reaſon why the Road was turn'd the other way. But it muſt be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd, at leaſt in great meaſure, by cutting throu the high grounds and raiſing the low. And this thing requires no ſmall labour and charge: but the Surveyor Generall can do it. [Note, that when I ſpeak of the Surveyor Generall, and what great things he will do; I chiefly mean the Curators or Directors whoſe Orders he executes. but for ſhortneſs I name only the Surveyor.] This therefore is the courſe we muſt ſteer, till we come to the Main Hill that goes up to <hi>Hampſted.</hi> And then we muſt bend to the right hand, ſtill aſcending gently and equally, till we meet with the old Road: which meeting place will be above the hard ſteep that toiles us at preſent.</p>
            <p>From hence we muſt follow the old Road, till we come to the top of the firſt Hill, where the great Elme ſtands. But ſince the Road is here very broad, and one ſide much higher then the other, we ſhould do well to keep on the lower ſide: which would much eaſe the Draught. Whereas now, the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd way is made to run up the higheſt ground: as if it were contrived, to make the draught as hard as may be. You will ſay this was done to keep the Way dryer. But the Way might be kept as dry on the lower ground, with ordinary Skill.</p>
            <p>From the top of this firſt Hill, to the lower end of the Town or Street, it would be a very eaſy Aſcent, if the Hollow were fill'd up that is between. And within the Town the Aſcent is not hard, nor can it be made eaſier. But to raiſe the Hollow now mention'd, I ſhall offer an Expedient; which will alſo make good the Way further on. But firſt I muſt tell you how things are there now. Toward the upper end of the Town the Way divides in two. One way turnes to the right hand, and leads to the greateſt Heighth of the Main Hill or Heath; and from thence goes towards the Left down a terrible
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64448:11"/>ſteep, to <hi>Hendon</hi> and thoſe Parts. The other way goes ſtraight forward juſt on the right hand the Wind-Mill: and over a high and narrow Ridge of ground, being a Spurre of the main Hill, upon which the Mill ſtands. The way being hardly paſſable (if at all) for Carts or Coaches. This Ridge of ground I would have cut throu to the bottome, and the Earth to be carried to the Hollow that is below. which will hold our Surveyor Tack for Ten or fifteen Weeks. And this is the Expedient I had to offer.</p>
            <p>Beyond the Windmill there is another Spurre, which is too bigg to be cut throu: nor will the Earth be of any uſe. But we may avoid it by bowing a little to the Left, ſtill plaining the way as we go and then bowing a little to the right, we may go down with an eaſy deſcent (partly along the Heath under the main Hill, and partly throu Incloſures) into <hi>Hendon</hi> Road. This new Snugg Way, being a near way withall, will be a mighty advantage to the whole little Country about <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> which hath now no other way to <hi>London,</hi> but one that is almoſt impaſſable. And it will give ſuch an advance to their Eſtates, that halfe of it paid as is above propoſed, would go a great way towards the Charge of the whole Worke, though it ſhould coſt ten thouſand pound. Otherwiſe a Toll may be ſet up to reimburſe the Charge, or at leaſt a good part of it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not now mention any more particular Works. And I doubt thoſe that have been mention'd, will ſeem to ſome people to be idle Fancies, and little better then Dreames. But I am in good earneſt: having great aſſurance, that the things may be done, and that in a very ſhort time, with ſuch a Sum as ten thouſand a yeare. And this is but the thouſandth part of the Revenue of <hi>England:</hi> which (as hath been noted) is ten thouſand thouſand pounds, or (to ſpeak ſhorter) ten Millions. And ſurely this is a ſmall proportion to be ſet aſide for a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Work, which brings ſo much Profit and Convenience, and ſo much Honour withall. Private great Workes and Buildings are a <hi>Species</hi> of Luxury: Publick great Workes that are unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, are meer Folly: but Publick great Workes that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial and uſeful, (and nothing is more ſo than High-Ways)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64448:11"/>are the Glory of a Country. But no Country wants them more then Ours; We have not Publick Spirits.</p>
            <p>As it hath been ſaid already, the great Works about the High Wayes will belong to the Surveyor Generall. And the other Surveyors will the while be doing, to very good Effect. So that in one dozen Yeares and leſs, there will be ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, ſuch a Transformation, as can hardly be imagined.</p>
            <p>Thus I have propoſed a Method for making good the High Wayes of <hi>England;</hi> which hitherto have been ſtrangely (I muſt not ſay ſhamefully and barbarouſly) neglected, to the great diſparagement and diſhonour of our Nation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ADDITAMENT.</head>
               <p>THE Summe here allotted to the Pariſh Surveyors may perhaps ſeem too little. But if it be thought fit, it may be doubled. that is, The Tax may be made ſix pence in the pound: whereof foure pence to go to the Pariſh Surveyors, the reſt continuing as before. And I confeſs this would bring the whole into good proportion, and make it compleat. But I durſt not propoſe ſo high a Tax.</p>
               <p>I doubt the Tax that hath been propoſed, will be thought too high by ſome people. But they ſhould conſider; That it muſt be laid out in their own Buſineſs, and plainly for their own Good. They will perhaps ſay, that however Compulſion is odious: and that they know what's good for themſelves, without being taught by Acts of Parliament. In anſwer, I confeſs they might ſpeak at this rate, if the Concern were private and particular. As it were very hard, if a Man ſhould be compell'd to make good Wayes, to his own Houſe or his owne Grounds: though it were ever ſo much for his Good. But in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Concern, and where a thing is to be done by many, and for the Good of Many; there muſt be Compulſion, or elſe the thing will never be done. As Men that have Lands in a Marſh, are compell'd by Law to contribute to the maintaining of the Banks and Walls. And High Wayes are of the ſame nature, tho not in the ſame degree. Moreover they ſhould remember,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64448:12"/>that they are already under Compulſion, and at Charge, about the High Wayes: tho in a Method that is uneffectuall.</p>
               <p>But ſtill they will ſay; Here is a certain Charge and Burden, ſettled upon our Land in the Nature of a Rent, by which our Land is plainly made worſe. To which I anſwer, that by the Amendment of the High Wayes their Lands will be plainly made better. Which thing is ſenſibly found, in <hi>Middleſex</hi> and other parts about <hi>London.</hi> Where Lands are much better and more valuable, and will yield a greater Rent, for being neer a good Road. And why ſhould this Burden ſeem more grievous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is certain? I think there is little difference, between having the Charge of the High Wayes to come to about four pence in the pound one yeare with another, and the paying of four pence a pound yearly to the High Wayes. But the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord muſt pay this certain Tax to his loſs and wrong. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that if the Law provide that the Tenants ſhall pay it, the Tenants will pay it, as they payd the Chimney Money.</p>
               <p>But the great Cry will be, that ten thouſand pound a yeare muſt be carried out of the Counties. and if it be anſwer'd, that it muſt be all laid out upon <hi>London</hi> Roads, which are a general Concern; they will reply, that moſt of it will be laid out upon the Roads neer <hi>London</hi> it ſelf: ſo that all <hi>England</hi> muſt contribute towards the Convenience and Glory of <hi>London.</hi> Here I muſt confeſs, that probably the Roads about <hi>London</hi> will be firſt look'd after becauſe, this City being the Center, the Roads neer it are more uſed by the people of the whole Kingdome, then any other Roads. and it is for the Glory and and Convenience of <hi>England,</hi> as well as of <hi>London,</hi> to have them made good. But within a ſhort time, the Aſſiſtance of this ten thouſand pound Stock will reach all parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where it is moſt wanted: either by acting ſeparately, or by helping the Surveyors of the Counties. Alſo it ſhould be again conſider'd, how light and eaſie the proportion is, of what muſt be thus advanced. It is but the thouſandth part, or a farthing in the pound. Moreover a great part of theſe Works about <hi>London</hi> may be done by Tolls. It is not long, ſince the Northern Road by <hi>Stamford</hi> hath been made good this way: and why ſhould not other Roads have the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage?</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64448:12"/>
               <p>Perhaps it may be feared, that upon the removing of ſo much Earth, (in the particular Workes beforemention'd, and in others of the like kind), this looſe Earth will be long in ſettling, and will in the mean time be hardly paſſable. But I am very confident; that the Earth being brought by Carts, it will be as hard and firme, in the very doing, as if it had lain ſeven yeares. This I know, that the carrying of Earth in Carts to a Poole Damme, is better than any Ramming.</p>
               <p>There ſhould be ſome Care taken alſo of Foot-wayes: which now, in moſt places are wholly neglected. Every great Road, (and every great Bridge likewiſe, after the Example of the new Bridge at <hi>Brentford</hi>), ſhould have a Foot Way by the ſide of it, Convenient and Pleaſant.</p>
               <p>Some think the High Wayes would be ſet right without more adoe, if the Juſtices of Peace had power to lay Money-Levies, when they ſee occaſion, upon the ſeverall Pariſhes: having power already to make one Pariſh help another. And I confeſs it would much further the Work. But the way lookes too Arbitrary. and in ſome places ſomething would be done, and in other places nothing would be done. and 'tis not occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Orders; but a conſtant courſe and application, under Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers who make it their buſineſs, that will do this Work effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and compleatly.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
